This video shows you how to download Python and also talks a bit about what a
هذا الفيديو يريك كيف تقوم بانزال بايثون  اضافة لذلك يتكلم قليلاً حول
program is. Programs are everywhere on your computer
ما هو البرنامج. البرامج موجودة في كل مكان على جهازك
and on the internet. Every time you use a web browser, play a
و كذلك على الانترنت. و في كل مرة تستخدم مستعرض الشبكة العنكبوتية أو تلعب
computer game or write a text message on your cell phone, you're using a program.
لعبة على الكومبيوتر أو تكتب رسالة نصية على تلفونك المحمول فأنت تقوم باستخدام برنامج
Even your operating system, such as OS10, Linux or Windows is a program.
حتى نظام التشغيل الخاص بك سواء كان  أو إس ١٠  أو لينوكس أو ويندوز فهو برنامج
A program is just a set of instructions. We say programs are run or executed.
البرنامج هو عبارة عن مجموعة من التعليمات. و نقول أن البرنامج يُنفذ أو يُشغل
Program, such as your operating system, run on hardware, like a cell phone, or
أي برنامج (كنظام التشغيل الخاص بك) يشتغل على أجهزة  (عتاد صلب)  كالهاتف المحمول
your laptop, or a tablet. But programs can also be run by other
أو الكومبيوتر المحمول أو الكومبيوتر اللوحي. و لكن البرامج يمكن أن يتم تشغيلها أيضا من قبل
programs. This is what happens when you play a game
برامج أخرى. هذا ما يحدث عندما تلعب لعبة
in a web browser. Your web browser knows how to run programs
في مستعرض الشبكة. فمستعرض الشبكة الخاص بك يعرف كيف يشغل برامج
written in a programming language called Java script.
مكتوبة بلغة برمجة تدعى جافا سكريبت
This webpage on wikipedia lists all the programming languages that anyone has ever
هذه الصفحة على موقع الويكيبديا تحوي لائحة بكافة لغات البرمجة التي قام احد ما
bothered to enter here, and there are hundreds of them.
بادخالها هنا و هناك المئات منها
You've probably heard of some of the programming languages.
لابد أنك سمعت عن بعض لغات البرمجة
We've heard a lot of them but certainly nowhere near all of them and we doubt that
نحن سمعنا بالعديد منها و لكن من المؤكد أننا لسنا قريبين من معرفتهم كلهم و نشك
anybody knows all the programming languages listed here.
أن يكون أحد يعرف كل لغات البرمجة المدرجة هنا
So, Python is a programming language, one of many.
حسنا. بايثون هي واحدة من عدة لغات برمجة
In order to learn Python programs, you need to download a program that
و لكي تتعلم برامج بايثون تحتاج الى تنزيل برنامج
understands that language much like your browser understands Javascript.
يفهم هذه اللغة مثلما يفهم مستعرض الشبكة الجافاسكريبت و لكي تتابع
In order to work through this course, you will need to download this program from
www.python.org هذه الدورة ستحتاج إلى تنزيل هذا البرنامج من.
python.org. There are two main versions of Python,
هناك نسختين أساسيتين من بايثون
Python two and Python three. We're going to use Python three.
بايثون 2 و بايثون 3. نحن سنقوم باستخدام بايثون 3
So, go ahead and click on Quick Links, and this is the download page for Python
و هذه هي صفحة تنزيلQuick Links حسنا. هيا انقر على
three, the current version. If you use Linux, you can use your package
بايثون ٣ النسخة الحالية. أذا كنت تستخدم لينوكس يمكنك استخدام  مدير الرزم
manager to install Python three. If you use Windows, this link is
الخاص بك لتنصيب البايثون  و اذا كنت تستخدم الويندوز فهذه
appropriate. If you use OS ten, one of the recent
الوصلة مناسبة لك. و اذا كنت تستخدم أحد النسخ الحديثة من أو إس ١٠
versions, at least, then this is the appropriate link to click.
فهذه الوصلة مناسبة لك
If you use a Mac, you may need to install something called TickleTK in order to run
TickleTK أما اذا كنت تستخدم ماكنتوش فربما تحتاج الى تنصيب شئ يسمى
the, the program we use to write python programs.
لتتمكن من تنفيذ البرنامج الذي نستخدمه لكتابة برامج بايثون
So, let's just scroll down to the bottom here, if you're a Mac user click on this
حسنا، دعنا ننتقل إلى الأسفل هنا و اذا كنت من مستخدمي ماكنتوش انقر
link, and then scroll down and download Active TCLE.5, .12 or whatever the newest
ActiveTCL8.5.9 هذه الوصلة ثم انزل إلى الأسفل و قم بتنزيل
version is. You are going to have to go to the active
active state أو أيأ كانت  النسخة الأحدث. عندها ستذهب إلى موقع
state website and then just click this big blue download button in order to get that.
و فقط انقر الزر الأزرق الكبير لتحصل عليها
To write our Python programs we are going to use a program called Idle named after
Idle لنقوم بكتابة برامج بايثون الخاصة بنا سنتسخدم برنامج اسمه
Eric Idle of Monty Python it will comes with Python.
الذي سمي تيمنا بايرك أيدل من مونتي بايثون و البرنامج موجود ضمن بايثون
Just double click on the icon and hopefully you see a window that looks like
فقط انقر مرتين على الأيقونة و نأمل أن تشاهد نافذة شبيهة بتلك